Today we're on דף ל"ז, Daf Lamed Zayin, or that's the דף
daf we pick up at the last line of ל"ו ע"ב, Lamed
Vav Amud Bet,
and we have the following,
or four lines from the bottom. אמר רבי חלבו, Amar Rabbi Chelbo,
Rabbi Chelbo said, חזינא ליה לרב הונא, Chazina lei le'Rav Huna, I
saw רב הונא, Rav Huna, דכרך ליה מאחד כלפי שמע, de'karach lei
mei-Echad klapei Shema, he wrapped his מזוזה mezuzah from אחד Echad towards
שמע, Shema, which is what we do, right? We wrap it up
from the left to the right. We scroll it up. ועושה פרשיותיה
סתומות, Ve-oseh parshiyoteha setumot, and he made its פרשיות סתומות, parshiyot stumot.
which is the way you wrap it?
Yeah, just the way you like turn it into a, like, yeah,
scroll it up, okay? Which makes a lot of sense, right? Because
anytime you do something, you want to be able to open it
at the beginning. So if you wrapped it from the back to
the front, then you open it at the beginning, which maybe the
חידוש chiddush since the whole idea of מזוזה mezuzah is you don't
open it. You know, just put it there.
Right,
correct. So
that's also important, but you still have to wrap it. ועושה פרשיות,
Ve-oseh parshiyot, I mean you still read it from right to left,
ועושה פרשיותיה סתומות, ve-oseh parshiyoteha setumot, and he make the פרשיות parshiyot
סתום. setum. Now if you ever see, you know, in—I always forget
what they do in the Artscroll, they might just visually do this,
but anyway in the חומש Chumash that I grew up with, the
classic חומש ויסטריץ, Chumash Vistretz, they would have פ’s pe and ס’s,
samech
right, which
Artscroll just visually does this. פ Pe means פתוח patuach and ס
samech means סתום. setum.
Surprisingly, although ס samech is less frequent if anybody ever noticed that,
it actually is less of a break. סתום Setum means closed, so
the normal way, although there's a big debate of actually
לשיטות lashitatos exactly what this would look like visually, the גמרא Gemara
doesn't spell it out, but the way we do it is that,
and that actually apparently was actually true from what I can read
in the Dead Sea scrolls of, you know, sort of מזוזות mezuzot
and ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah and so on as well, is that
סתום setum means it's closed, so a line of text ends in
the middle of a line, then there's a, like, a certain amount
of white space, and then the next פסוק pasuk begins on the
same line towards the end. So there's like a little gap of
white space in the middle of a line. It's closed between two
blocks of text on either end of the line. So that's, you
know, like a paragraph grade break but not a section break. And
פתוח patuach is that it's open, that it stopped in the middle
of the line, there's white space till the end, and then the
next text starts at the next line, and that's a larger break,
meaning a larger paragraph break, you know, a section break. Actually, תוספות
Tosafos has an, says, quotes ירושלמי Yerushalmi and other opinions that maybe
even an idea of a פתוח patuach where it's white till the
end and then a whole other unwritten white line, blank line, and
then you start a whole actually next line down, you know, like
we would like hit like two line feeds basically to get, you
know, which is a larger section break which you don't have a
מסורה mesorah for in the תורה, Torah, but actually again in some
of the Dead Sea scrolls they have found that some texts employ
that when conceptually, you know, makes sense, you're dealing with even a
larger section break. But פתוח patuach is, you know, normal different פרשיות.
parshiyot I feel like nine letters wide or something?
That's discussed in תוספות, Tosafos, it's not discussed in the גמרא. Gemara.
If we have a chance we'll read a little bit of תוספות.
Tosafos. So פתוח patuach is, you know, is a larger break, סתום
setum is a smaller break. Now the question here by the שמע
Shema is the following, which is that where the שמע Shema appears
in the תורה, Torah,
it is סתום setum with the next פרשה. parsha.
Wish we had a
תנ"ך Tanach open.
Do you have...
oh, I can look for you.
Yeah,
okay.
Right, so almost right before here.
Yeah, great, right, so you can look at this, right. This is
a
פתוח, patuach, right, goes straight to the end, and this is a
סתום, setum, it's very visual, you know, that since here there's a
sense of continuity and here there's a sense of break, right? So
that's the difference between פתוח patuach and סתום. setum. Now if you
look at שמע, Shema, you will see the following.
Wait, but the way you write it in the מזוזה mezuzah isn't,
we don't... I know, right, right, I'm going to talk about that.
Okay, so here by the שמע Shema there's a break before the
שמע, Shema, שמע Shema starts the topic, but at the end of
ובשעריך, u'visharecha, והיה כי יביאך, ve-hayah ki yeviacha, it's סתום, setum,
it's not a much of a break, right? You see that? And
similarly now, so the question is going to be how are you
going to situate... well let's look at what the והיה אם שמוע
v'hayah im shamoa looks like. This is in the next פרשה. parsha.
Okay, so והיה אם שמוע v'hayah im shamoa here, והיה אם שמוע
תשמעו אל מצותי אשר אנכי מצוה v'hayah im shamoa tishme'u el mitzvotai
asher anochi metzaveh is also סתום setum with the one preceding it.
So logically, the שמע Shema runs into the one following it, although
it's not והיה אם שמוע, v'hayah im shamoa, but it's סתום, setum,
it's more continuous. והיה אם שמוע v'hayah im shamoa is continuous with
what precedes it. So presumably if you're going to put שמע Shema
next to והיה אם שמוע, v'hayah im shamoa, you're going to do
it סתום, setum, that's what most reflects the way it's written in,
well, thank you, we're going to see an opposite opinion in a
minute, but if you wanted to reflect the way it appears in
the text, you would say שמע Shema is followed with a סתום,
setum, והיה אם שמוע v'hayah im shamoa is preceded... He did with
the סתום, setum, let's write with a סתום, setum, and that's what
he did. He did the פרשיות סתומות. parshiyot stumot. Let's see, well,
you will see what the response would be in a minute. I
did want to just say one thing because we're not at all
going to focus on the curling up, this is taken for granted
that that's what they do, and actually there's a, goes back a
long time, this whole idea of the belief of מזוזות mezuzot as
also some type of charms to protect against מזיקים, mazikim, and the
רמב"ם Rambam obviously comes out very strongly against that and people that
would write names of angels on the backside of the מזוזה mezuza
after it was all scrolled up. Anyway, the idea that it doesn't
really halachically have to be scrolled up, but I mentioned this because
I went, I mentioned this to some people ten of yesterday, my
sister-in-law had this house which had you know, like for fun, like
one of these real like almost secret passages, something that looked like
a built-in bookcase, and it was on hinges, you know, on the
back, and you opened it up and it opened to the stairways
up to the attic. Okay, the thing was where do you put
the מזוזה mezuza because the bookcase is totally within the hole, and
any מזוזה mezuza it would bang into any מזוזה mezuza you tried
to put in the archway. So I said, it's not a problem.
You take a piece of parchment, you lay it flat, you wrap
it in saran wrap and you do it flat against the wall,
right? מזוזה Mezuza doesn't have to be a rolled up thing in
three dimensions, it can be totally flat against the wall. But normally
we think about it obviously as כרוך, karuch, which is what they
would do. And also you could have just dug a hole into
the frame like they do in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but I don't, I
think it was like metal or something, I don't think that would
happen. Anyway, okay, so now.
The thing is,
he, רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva would scroll up. You don't have to.
You never have to? לכתחילה, Lechatchila, that's just the way they would
do it. I'm not sure. I'd have to see. I don't know
if anybody has
seen the way...
oh man.
It's open more.
Right.
Then you have more of an... right. Well we will see, we
will come up to גמרות Gemarot where the whole idea of מזוזה
mezuza as a form of protection and whatever, you know, as you
can imagine the רמב"ם Rambam is against all of those more sort
of superstitious approaches.
Right, people think about the מזוזה mezuza as some sort of protection.
And people who aren't Jewish.
Right. And how about the fact that people wear little מזוזות mezuzot
around their neck. Well anyway, that's surprisingly, you know, for the most
part the גמרא Gemara is pretty free from this type of sort
of superstitious type of thing. Here it never really endorses it, but
it records some of that stuff around some of the מזוזות. mezuzot.
So we will take a look. So let's take a look. And
he made the פרשיות parshiyot. סתומות. setumot, מיתיבי, Meitivei, they asked on
this, אמר רבי שמעון
אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Shimon Elazar, Rebbe Shimon Elazar says, רבי מאיר היה
כותבה על דוכסוסטוס. Rabbi Meir haya kotevah al duchsostos. This רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir would write the מזוזה mezuza on דוכסוסטוס. duchsostos. Now רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir is one of the most well-known scribes in the
תנ"ך Tanakh and תנ"ך Tanakh in the תלמוד. Talmud. I mean he
actually, you know, that was his profession and he often has things
to say about how things are written. So it doesn't just say
רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, רבי מאיר היה כותבה, Rabbi Meir
haya kotevah, he would actually write it.
He just invoked the wire in the light.
Right, she's not getting a good reception right in front of me.
Okay, anyway,
okay, so he would write it on דוכסוסטוס. duchsostos. Now what's דוכסוסטוס?
duchsostos? דוכסוסטוס Duchsostos is a type of a קלף. klaf. You know
what, we'll get back to what דוכסוסטוס duchsostos is in a minute,
let's first finish the idea, but it's a certain way in which
it's a certain part of the animal skin they would use to
make the parchment. Like the bottom part? Yeah, we'll talk about it
in a minute. Anyway, he would write it on the דוכסוסטוס, duchsostos,
which is a Greek word by the way, כמין דף, k'min daf,
and it would be like a page, which means what? So it
means that it would be presumably as Dov was saying, it would
not be two columns, it would be one column. רש"י Rashi also
says ארוכה וקצרה, arucha u'ketzara, it would be narrow and I mean
sometimes if you look at some מזוזות, mezuzot, some are wide, some
are only a few lines, some wide and some are, most are
wider than they are long, but apparently he would write it more
like a column of text which would mean long and narrow. ועושה,
V'oseh, so again, is that clear that that's a פסק הלכה psak
halacha or is that just what his style was? You know, he
was a סופר. sofer. Okay, ועושה, v'oseh,
and he would do, ועושה רווח מלמעלה ורווח מלמטה, v'oseh revach mil'ma'ala
v'revach mil'mata, he would make a margin above and below. We had
learned about that
before by a ספר תורה Sefer Torah we learned about a margin,
here it's by a מזוזה, mezuza, top of 32A. ועושה פרשיותיה פתוחות,
V'oseh parshiyoteha petuchot, and he made the פרשיות פתוחות. parshiyot petuchot That's
really our upshot, okay, is the idea that it has to be
פתוח. patuach. Although the other stuff might also have included הלכה. halacha.
But what would we care? Okay, narrow, right, so some of this
might be style, might not be הלכה. halacha. But anyway, פרשיות parshiyot
פתוחות petuchot. presumably is a halachic position as well. So we had
said before סתומות. stumot. ואמרתי לו, V'amarti lo, and I said to
him, says רבי שמעון אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon Elazar, רבי מה טעם, Rebbi
mah ta'am, why are you doing it this way? Presumably why are
you making the פרשיות parshiyot פתוחות petuchot since they appear סתומות stumot
in the Torah. אמר לי, Amar li, and he said to me,
הואיל ואין סמוכות מן התורה, ho'il v'ein smuchot min haTorah, because in
the Torah they are not juxtaposed. The whole idea of סמוכות smuchot
is, you know, is a visual reality that reflects the idea that
this is continuous like, you know, flow with the following text. It's
not the same פרשה, parsha, but in one sort of continuous flow
and here they are actually not juxtaposed in the Torah, I'm not
going to make them סתומות stumot when I write the מזוזה. mezuza.
Again, what's interesting is they didn't have a tradition, this was all
based on logic. Yes.
Well the way it's,
I
mean
רש"י... Rashi...
Oh,
you mean he's saying that either way would be okay since they're
not סמוכות smuchot I don't have to retain the pagination of this
and therefore I'm choosing I can really do it either way. So
that's a good point, the Gemara is going to discuss in a
minute when he says פתוחות ptuchot does he mean even פתוחות even
ptuchot or only פתוחות? only ptuchot? That's the difference between the way
I'm reading it and you're reading it. The way I'm reading it
is that it's incorrect to do it סתומות. stumot. סתומות stumot suggests
a certain logical continuity between the two פרשיות parshiot which is not
really the way they are.
They're really all the other things, what was the other thing that
he mentioned? Also an issue of custom but not a requirement.
That's true. Okay, so the Gemara will discuss that in a minute,
but the two ways of understanding the answer: if you say that
he's just saying, look, you're not justified to make them סתומות stumot
because they're not juxtaposed in the פסוקים, psukim, then it's actually you
should not make them סתומות. stumot. If it's the way Dov is
saying, it says there's no need to make them סתומות stumot because
you know because they're not dealing with continuous text, so that is
a question of whether he would do דווקא פתוחות davka ptuchot or
even פתוחות. even ptuchot. We'll see about that in a minute.
Okay.
Now, ואמר רבי חננאל אמר רב הלכה כרבי שמעון אלעזר, v'amar Rabbi
Chananel amar Rav halacha k'Rabbi Shimon Elazar, we rule like Rabbi Shimon
Elazar. Again, it's funny nobody even gave a פסק psak here, you
know he's telling a story and he's telling about how רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir the סופר sofer would write the text, but presumably we
understood that this discussion of פתוחות ptuchot and סתומות stumot was a
הלכתי halachic one and that we are ruling like this story, so
we're ruling that you do פתוחות. ptuchot. And before we said you
do סתומות, stumot, how do you reconcile?
And then everyone's paskening whoever this is that
about the issue of the דף daf and the דוכסוסטוס? duchsustos?
Right, right, well we'll discuss those other pieces later but that does
not it's not our focus right now. So let's take a look.
So the Gemara says מאי לאו אפתוחות? mai lav aptuchot? So this
is exactly part of the question: when we rule like this story,
are we not ruling relating to the issue of פתוחות? ptuchot? So
the Gemara says לא ארווח. lo arevach. No, maybe we're ruling about
the margins, she recorded the margins that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir did
margins so we're ruling that margins are required. Now this is a
חידוש chiddush because as I mentioned to you yesterday and רבקה Rivka
brought us in, oh, I printed them out actually. Avi? Yeah, those.
You want? Not the last thing which is a מהר"א Mahara but
if you print out the first text. No, not the last
thing, the other side. This is which is first and which is
last here. Let's hand these out.
This is I uploaded this to the website so so for
Rachel and Jed you can see it on on the blog.
Okay, this actually somebody went, he wrote a whole thing, it took
me forever to find this on the web because any printing of
what it looked like the Dead Sea Scroll תפילין tefillin looks like
is impossible, it's like such tiny type and you can't read it
and so on. So somebody did a whole מלאכה melacha to transcribe
it. You see he even tells you the attempt he made to
transcribe it. But now finally it's actually very readable. The left hand
side is not just a transcription, but you know almost a visual
reproduction of what it looked like on the script. And if you
take a look here at it, right, this is from the תפילין
tefillin אלה הדברים אשר דבר משה אל כל ישראל בעבר הירדן. eleh
hadvarim asher diber Moshe el kol Yisrael b'ever haYarden. So actually it's
interesting it starts much before, right?
שמע ישראל השם אלוקינו השם אחד ואהבת Shma Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu Hashem
Echad v'ahavta near the end. So there is a little פתוח patuach
there, a סתום satum excuse me I should say. But anyway no
תגין tagin certainly, a very simple type of a thing. But as
you look at the thing on the right you will see that
there is absolutely no margins. Basically when they wrote תפילין, tefillin, I
don't know if they found any מזוזות, mezuzot, but when they wrote
תפילין tefillin they did not leave any margins, they wrote a very
simple text, they basically wrote it on tiny little pieces of קלף
klaf because they you know
produced the major size בתים batim too. Did they misspell?
ואהבת? v'ahavta? שמע ישראל השם אלוקינו השם אחד ואהבת, Shma Yisrael Hashem
Elokeinu Hashem Echad v'ahavta, they left out a ה heh after the
ה. heh. Oh yeah look. Where? Right, look at the שמע. Shma.
שמע ישראל השם אלוקינו השם אחד ואהבת, Shma Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu Hashem
Echad v'ahavta, they left out a ה heh in השם. Hashem. So
there's no ה heh in השם? Hashem?
Oh my god look at that. Okay anyway. They misspell השם? Hashem?
All right, right. Anyway, so, so, apparently like for example,
just to loosely, do you know that veal is a byproduct of
the dairy industry? Right, because you know because you only are interested
in the female cows, so therefore because they produce milk what happens
to the male cow? You basically make it into veal. So קלף,
klaf, and the reason I say this is קלף klaf for תפילין
tefillin and מזוזות mezuzot were byproducts of the קלף klaf that they
made for ספרים sfarim because basically you know when you have to
cut from natural leather a קלף klaf you have these little שיריים
shirayim on the side that are not nice sizes. They use those
little שיריים shirayim for תפילין tefillin and מזוזות mezuzot that they stuffed
onto little scraps on and they squeezed everything in here. So anyway
there is no margin. And also because you don't look at it
the aesthetics are not so important, right, you don't look at it.
So there is a חידוש chiddush that you do actually have a
margin. by the מזוזה, mezuzah, which is what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is saying. So that's where we rule that you have a margin
by the מזוזה mezuzah and that's how we're ruling like רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, we are not ruling like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir in
terms of the פתוח סתום patuach satum issue. The גמרא's Gemara not
done with this, let's keep on going. So אמר רב מנשיא בר
יעקב ואמרי לה אמר רב שמואל בר יעקב, Amar Rav Menashya bar
Yaakov ve-amrei lah amar Rav Shmuel bar Yaakov, I'm sorry, וכמה רווח,
ve-kamah revach, how much is the margin? אמר רב מנשיא בר יעקב
ואמרי לה אמר רב שמואל בר יעקב, Amar Rav Menashya bar Yaakov
ve-amrei lah amar Rav Shmuel bar Yaakov, כמלא אטבא דספרי, kemelo itba
de-safrei, like the width of an אטבא דספרי. itba de-safrei. What's an
אטבא דספרי? itba de-safrei? רש״י Rashi basically says it was like a
paperclip or a placeholder. If you look at רש״י, Rashi, אטבא דספרי
גלויין, itba de-safrei geluyin, I don't know that is... anyway, אטבא דוק,
itba duk, like a cracked piece of
wood הנושך דפי קונטרס שלא יכפלו ha-noshekh dapei kuntras she-lo yikhpalu that
holds the pages down so you basically clip pages together here so
they don't fold over. So some type of like a paperclip, presumably
something very narrow. Yes we require a margin, but not like we
talked about before by a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, three fingers, four
fingers, whatever, a tiny little thin margin for a מזוזה mezuzah because
again this is not usually seen so the issues of הידור hiddur
are not exactly the same. So that's how we rule like רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir in terms of the margin.
אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף, Amar lei Abaye le-Rav Yosef, so אביי
Abaye said to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, הא לאו תשפרתא, ha lav
tishparta, do you not hold
דכי אמר רב... dekhi amar Rav... don't you hold that when רב
Rav said that we rule like... where were we, hold on... that
when we rule like רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
we're talking about the margins and not the issue of פתוח patuach
and סתום? satum? How do we know that? והא רב אית ליה
מנהגא. ve-ha Rav it lei minhaga. רב, Rav, this is an amazing
phrase in the גמרא, Gemara, רב Rav normally is goes by מנהג.
minhag. Now it doesn't mean that we're that like we're about to
come up to פסח Pesach where everybody knows there's a millions of
מנהגים, minhagim, it doesn't mean that you believe that you keep customs.
What that actually means, אית ליה מנהגא, it lei minhaga, is a
very important halakhic question about how strongly do practices influence פסק הלכה,
psak halakhah, what the accepted practice is. Scholars will distinguish between two
or two things which are the same in Hebrew but different. I
just switched if you noticed from custom to practice. In modern Hebrew
they have they use two words. One is מנהג minhag and the
other is נוהג. nohag. מנהג minhag is a custom which basically means
a non-halakhic, non-mandated activity. That's a custom. נוהג nohag is a practice,
what have the people been doing? So the real question is whether
how much is הלכה halakhah influenced by what it says in the
ספרים sefarim or the rabbinic traditions and how much is it influenced
by what the people are actually doing. We normally, Haym Soloveitchik wrote
a whole article about this, Rupture and Reconstruction, etc. We become we
have become a very text-based tradition and therefore we're sometimes scandalized when
we think,
oh like well even though the גמרא Gemara says this but practice
is something else, maybe we should reinterpret the גמרא Gemara based on
practice. That's our sort of attitude to we think it's all based
on text. But mostly traditional societies it wasn't based on text, it
was based on the tradition. It was based on what was handed
down and what people have been doing. To the point that when
you read Jacob Katz, who's like the first real big historian of
הלכה, halakhah, he says when תוספות Tosafot came along and and tried
to
suggest refining the הלכה halakhah or changing the הלכה halakhah whatever based
on what it said in the גמרא, Gemara, they were seen as
the reformers, as the non-traditionalists.
Our practice has been this, you want to change it because of
something is written in some book somewhere, in a גמרא Gemara somewhere.
And so that's why we now read תוספות Tosafot and we're like
surprised at how frequently תוספות, Tosafot, if the גמרא Gemara says X
and the practice is Y, תוספות Tosafot makes their peace with the
practice and reinterprets the גמרא Gemara to coincide with the practice. But
nevertheless תוספות Tosafot has a dialectic going on and they're prepared sometimes
to adjust practice, at least bring practice under the microscope of the
text. So in a real traditional society it's the we think that
the חידוש chiddush of תוספות Tosafot is that they reinterpret text based
on practice. But in a real traditional society it's the practice that
dominates. Anyway, so this is a very important question about how much
does
פסק הלכה psak halakhah influenced by canonized sources, I don't care whether
it's written or oral, as opposed to practice. And a lot of
this is, I'll just say one last thing and then we'll start
return to the גמרא, Gemara, a lot of this has to do
also with what position the rabbi held and a lot of this
unfortunately is a reality nowadays. If you compare the משנה ברורה Mishnah
Berurah to the
ערוך השלחן, Arukh HaShulchan, the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah is all based
on what the ראשונים Rishonim and אחרונים Akharonim said and then he'll
say this is the הלכה halakhah and we have to correct everybody
who's doing the wrong thing. Okay, he says that a lot of
times. And the ערוך השלחן Arukh HaShulchan will say even though the
גמרא Gemara says this, מנהג ישראל תורה היא minhag Yisrael Torah hi
or מנהג ישראל קדושים minhag Yisrael kedoshim and it's a מצוה mitzvah
on us to figure out how to sustain the מנהג ישראל minhag
Yisrael and he'll reinterpret the sources based on that. And sometimes he'll
even just start by saying yes מחלוקת machloket blah blah blah but
nevertheless the מנהג minhag in ליטא Lita has always been the following
and therefore that's what we do. So and part of that had
to do not just with different orientations but that the משנה ברורה
Mishnah Berurah was a rabbi in a ישיבה yeshiva and the ערוך
השלחן Arukh HaShulchan was a rabbi of a community. And הלכה Halakha
has traditionally been פסקנט paskaned by rabbis in the communities, not by
the rabbis in the ישיבה, yeshiva, which is a big problem nowadays,
where it's the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva or my ישיבה yeshiva back
in my ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva back in Israel is פסקנט paskaned
for me, you know? So that sense of פסקנט paskaned in a
vacuum. So this is the question where beautiful גמרא gemara that is
actually saying how much does מנהג, minhag, meaning practice, not מנהג, minhag,
influence פסק? psak? So how could you say that you think that
רב Rav suggested, back to our point, that we go by פתוח,
patuach, that we פסקן paskan פתוחות? ptuchot? רב Rav says we allow
מנהג minhag influences פסק psak and therefore what? והאידנא V'haidna nowadays נהג
עלמא, nahag alma, the accepted practice is that the מזוזות mezuzot are
written with סתומות, stumot, with the you know, only with the partial
break in the line, not the full line feed. So therefore when
רב Rav says we פסקן paskan like רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar, he must mean about something else, he must mean
about the margins, because when it comes to how the מזוזה mezuzah
is written, clearly he's going to go by the practice, which is
סתומות. stumot. ורבי מאיר VeRabbi Meir though. Okay, well
we'll worry about רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but רב Rav at least
is going to פסקן, paskan, he's not going to פסקן paskan against
the practice. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara says like this. Now
we're going actually have this little digression about being influenced by practice.
דאמר רבה אמר רב כהנא, De'amar Rabbah amar Rav Kahana, רבה Rabbah
said in the name of רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, אמר רב, amar
Rav, and in the name of רב, Rav, and here's רב, Rav,
how we know that רב Rav goes by practice. אם יבוא אליהו
ויאמר, Im yavo Eliyahu veyomar, if אליהו Eliyahu were to come and
tell us חולצין במנעל, choltzin bemin'al, and you do חליצה, chalitzah, you
can even use מנעל, min'al, which is like a classic
shoe. I'm not now going to discuss what they look like differently,
but that's not our issue. Anyway, if אליהו... Eliyahu... so there's a
question about this מנעל. min'al. If אליהו הנביא Eliyahu HaNavi were to
come and say you could use it, שומעין לו, shomin lo, we
would listen to him, we would what?
I'll discuss that in a minute. Okay, in the גמרא gemara it
was not so clear. Okay, שומעין לו, shomin lo, we would listen
to him. אין חולצין בסנדל, Ein choltzin besandal, however, if he was
to say that a סנדל sandal was invalid, אין שומעין לו, ein
shomin lo, we would refuse to listen to him. Why? שכבר נהגו
העם בסנדל. Shekvar nahagu ha'am besandal. We already have been established the
practice to use the סנדל sandal and therefore we would reject what
אליהו Eliyahu would say. Now, I must say, you know, that the
point here is it's unfortunately it's not just like, you know, even
if all of the rabbis would say X, it's if אליהו Eliyahu
would say X. So it's not really... it doesn't say as much
as you would like, because we also have another principle that, you
know, אין נביא רשאי לחדש דבר, ein navi rasha'i lechadesh davar, that
אליהו Eliyahu does not have any greater weight in הלכה Halakha discourse
than any rabbi. He maybe even has less weight, you know, who
gave him סמיכה? smicha?
So the
point is that saying that מנהג minhag wins out over אליהו הנביא
Eliyahu HaNavi is not necessarily saying that מנהג minhag wins out over
weighty canonized sources. There is a line in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi of
מנהג מבטל הלכה, minhag mevattel halacha, which goes even further. Okay, but
again, this is when there's ambiguity in the sources. You know, the
question is, do you go by common practice so much even if
the sources seem very black and white? So these are all questions
about how weighty is common practice, again not מנהג, minhag, not custom,
but common practice when it comes to פסק. psak. So anyway, here
we see that רב Rav says you... מנהג minhag would win out
over אליהו הנביא Eliyahu HaNavi if something is an adopted practice, we're
not even going to let אליהו הנביא Eliyahu HaNavi tell us otherwise.
And therefore he would not go against the adopted practice to do
the מזוזות mezuzot that are סתומות. stumot. Okay, now we're just going
to end this little discussion about חליצה. chalitzah.
ורב יוסף אמר, VeRav Yosef amar, and רב יוסף Rav Yosef says
a different version, אמר רב כהנא אמר רב, amar Rav Kahana amar
Rav, אם יבוא אליהו ויאמר, im yavo Eliyahu veyomar, אין חולצין במנעל,
ein choltzin bemin'al, not if אליהו Eliyahu tells us to use a
מנעל. min'al. If he were to tell us not to use a
מנעל, min'al, שומעין לו, shomin lo, we would be prepared to follow
that. אין חולצין בסנדל, Ein choltzin besandal, don't use a סנדל, sandal,
אין שומעין לו, ein shomin lo, we would not listen to him,
שכבר נהגו העם בסנדל shekvar nahagu ha'am besandal because that's already the
established practice. Now what's the difference? Meaning clearly the מנעל min'al was
not as well-established as the סנדל. sandal. It was like debated whether
it could be used, maybe some people used it, some people didn't.
So since it was more ambiguous, they're saying for that there isn't
an established practice, we would listen to אליהו. Eliyahu. So one says
we'd listen to אליהו Eliyahu not to use, the other said we'd
listen to אליהו Eliyahu to use it. But what's the difference? At
the end of the day, you admit that this is an ambiguous
status and whether you use a סנדל sandal or not, it's you
know, and that we'd follow... whether you use a מנעל min'al and
we'd follow אליהו. Eliyahu. So the גמרא gemara says מאי בינייהו? mai
beinayhu? What's the difference? ורמינה Urmina מאי בינייהו? mai beinayhu? מנעל לכתחילה
איכא בינייהו. Min'al l'chatchila ika beinayhu. That the difference is that the
one that says we'd listen to אליהו Eliyahu not to use it
is assuming that right now it's acceptable to use it. And even
so, we'd stop using it based on אליהו Eliyahu because it's not
like a well-established practice. The one that says we'd listen to אליהו
Eliyahu to use it is assuming that right now it's pretty rare
to use it, it's not so much accepted, not like unacceptable, but
it's not, you know, established. Okay, so that's a question about what
you would do for חליצה. chalitzah. At the end of the day
though, we're saying that if something is an established practice, we're not
even going to let אליהו הנביא Eliyahu HaNavi come and change it.
Now again, it would be nicer if we didn't talk about אליהו
הנביא, Eliyahu HaNavi, but we talked about like even if there was
a מסורה, mesorah, even if there was a משנה, mishnah, even if
there was a ברייתא, braita, that we didn't say. We said אליהו
הנביא, Eliyahu HaNavi, who also has a questionable weight within הלכה, Halakha,
but we are putting it down say that רב Rav gives significant
weight to what the established practice of the people is and therefore
רב Rav is certainly not going to... to say that we do
anything other than סתומות Setumot by the מזוזה. Mezuzah. You had a
question?
So what you're saying is if there's something that's questionable and we
know for sure, and you know, then we may listen to אליהו
הנביא. Eliyahu Hanavi. Right. But if he's going against something we know
for...
well, if it's an established practice, right, well-established practice, that we're not...
if there's been a little bit ambivalent, some people do it, some
people don't, that's not like a consensus practice. So then we'd listen
to אליהו. Eliyahu. But if there's been a consensus well-established practice, we're
not going to...
what would we say if he actually went against the הלכה? Halacha?
Was that that whole story with the תנור של עכנאי? Tanur shel
Achnai?
Well yeah, I mean the question is how far does it go,
or what do you mean if the מנהג Minhag went against the
הלכה? Halacha? That's the ירושלמי Yerushalmi about מנהג מבטל הלכה, Minhag mevattel
Halacha, which is sometimes quoted by the גאונים. Geonim. How far do
you take that? But at least if there's a way of reinterpreting
the sources and there's some ambivalence, you know, that's about... this is
really a central central issue of פסק, Psak, how much you just
look at text and how much you look at what's been established
and practiced in the community. Now I will say one final thing
about this historically before we move on, which is that חיים סולובייצ'יק,
Chaim Soloveitchik, you know, points out that the אשכנזים Ashkenazim were much
more inclined to go by, use the weight of common practice than
the ספרדים Sefardim who went by text. And he says a lot
of this has to do with how you perceive your own community.
אשכנזי Ashkenazi communities were more cloistered and separate from large outside society.
They also had, you know, martyred themselves over the Crusades. So the
אשכנזים Ashkenazim are going to look at their practices of their community
and say of course, you know, we're פרום, Frum, of course we
do the right thing. So they won't question the פרומקייט Frumkeit of
the people and therefore the validity of the practice. Whereas, you know,
in ספרדי Sefardi communities, which were more like modern orthodox, they were
more integrated into the larger outside world. Not everybody was so מחמיר
Machmir on every little הלכה. Halacha. When it came the idea, the
threat of like convert or die, a lot of them chose to
convert, you know. So therefore when the ספרדי ראשונים Sefardi Rishonim looked
at their own communities, they were not so sure we could assume
that all their practices were so פרום. Frum. Maybe sometimes they're doing
things different than the גמרא Gemara because our community isn't as careful
as it needs to be. So the question about whether you look
at what your community is doing and say that this has real
weight and we can trust that this is a legitimate practice is
to some degree influenced also by your perception of your community. So
that I think is also very interesting in terms of thinking about
aspects of פסק. Psak. Okay. So now we go on. The גמרא
Gemara says like this.
אלא לאו שמע מינה Ela lav shema mina רב Rav you see
if we're ruling like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it cannot be about
the פתוחות, Petuchot, because the practice is סתום, Satum, it must be
about the margin. שמע מינה. Shema mina. That's a good proof.
Because the practice changed over time? We still do it, we still
do... No, we do סתום, Satum, right? If somebody asked one to
write פתוחה, Petuchah, we couldn't do it
because the practice is against it. Well, the question is it switched
from practice to פסק. Psak. We're now ruling like... you know, we're
ruling like the position of פתוחה. Petuchah. Whether it's actually פסול בדיעבד
Pasul bediavad is a good question. By all these things, you know,
there's one question about where are we getting this from? Are these
just traditions, which the גמרא Gemara sort of labels a lot of
these things as הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai, or are they
things that we're just figuring out our own sense of the aesthetics,
which seems to be somewhat or other considerations, which seems to be
what's going on here. And then the other question is and what
happens if you violate them? Is it still כשר Kasher or is
it מעכב? Me'akkev? And that's, you know, largely not discussed in the
גמרא, Gemara, it's discussed later. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. So what is it? So everything depends and everything is debated.
So let's keep on going here. רב נתן בר יצחק אמר Rav
Natan bar Yitzchak amar now here this already directly addresses your question
Michael. רב נתן בר יצחק Rav Natan bar Yitzchak says מצוה לעשותן
סתומות. Mitzvah la-asotan setumot. לכתחילה, Lechatechila,
you know what, the position that we said before was correct, not
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you make it סתום Satum because that's the
way it appears in the תורה. Torah. ואם עבדינן פתוחות, Ve-im avdinan
petuchot, but if you did פתוחות Petuchot like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
chose to do, then שפיר דמי, Shapir dami, that's also acceptable. At
the end of the day, these are not juxtaposed in the תורה
Torah the way they are in the מזוזה, Mezuzah, so you have
a certain amount of latitude. You're supposed to do it סתומות Stumot
to reflect the idea that, you know, each פרשה Parsha by itself
is סתום, Satum, but since they're not juxtaposed in the תורה, Torah,
פתוחות Petuchot also works. ומאי פתוחות דקאמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר? U-mai
petuchot dikamar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar? Now here is how going back
to what you said though. This could even be what רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir said, we could even be פסקנינג paskening רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir because רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar quotes רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir to say פתוחות. Petuchot. You know what פתוחות Petuchot
means? דקאמר אף פתוחות, Dekamar af petuchot, even פתוחות Petuchot is acceptable.
Now it's not exactly רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir because he made סתומות
לכתחילה Stumot lechatechila and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir made פתוחות לכתחילה. Petuchot
lechatechila. Okay, but at least it's saying it's not really in contradiction,
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said פתוחות Petuchot also works, you have a
free choice in terms of how you want to do it. Okay,
so the הלכה Halacha is the way the גמרא Gemara concludes here
is that לכתחילה Lechatechila you're supposed to do סתומות, Stumot, which reflect
how they appear in the תורה Torah when they're in their context,
but בדיעבד Bediavad you could do פתוחות Petuchot because these were not
juxtaposed actually in the תורה Torah itself. All right. Now the גמרא
Gemara says לימא מסייע Lema mesaya let me try to support this
idea that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is open to doing it oh
that was not meant as a pun anyway, is open to doing
it סתום. Satum. So he says... כיוצא בו kiyotze bo because here
we have a ברייתא braita in שבת. Shabbat. It says with the
question is whether you can use old parchment from one thing for
another. So in a similar way, ספר תורה שבלה Sefer Torah shebala
ותפילין שבלו, ut'fillin shebalu, if a ספר תורה Sefer Torah has worn
away and תפילין t'fillin have worn away with age, the parchment, so
you can no longer use it as a ספר תורה Sefer Torah
or תפילין, t'fillin, can you reuse the parchment? So what do we
say? אין עושים מהם מזוזה, ein osim mehem mezuza,
you cannot use them, those parchments to make... You mean writing over
the parchment?
No, or cut out...
or cut out
the שמע Shema and והיה אם שמוע
V'haya Im Shamoa and stick it in your מזוזה. mezuza. That you
cannot do. לפי שאין מורידין מקדושה חמורה לקדושה
קלה, lefi she'ein moridin mik'dusha chamura lik'dusha kala, because ספר תורה Sefer
Torah and תפילין t'fillin has a higher קדושה k'dusha than the שמע.
Shema. Why? Well, ספר תורה Sefer Torah is the whole ספר, sefer,
but also because it's just larger, it's more פרשיות, parshiyot, even if
you just compared the תפילין t'fillin to the מזוזה, mezuza, they have
a higher קדושה k'dusha and therefore you cannot lower the parchment from
a higher קדושה k'dusha to a lower קדושה. k'dusha.
I wanted to sew my מזוזה mezuza into...
If you wanted to cut out your שמע Shema from your מזוזה
mezuza and
put it into
your תפילין, t'fillin, you could do that. Into your של ראש shel
rosh where it has different... or ספר תורה Sefer Torah even. ספר
תורה Sefer Torah if you sewed it in presumably, presumably. Okay.
I'm sorry, let me just understand one thing just to make sure
about... So the פתוחות, p'tuchot, we're just... I mean the סתומות, stumot,
we're only talking about between שמע Shema and והיה אם שמוע V'haya
Im Shamoa or do you even start the שמע Shema in the
middle?
Not start the שמע Shema in the beginning, we're talking about between
שמע Shema and והיה אם שמוע. V'haya Im Shamoa. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: הא מורידין, ha moridin, if the issue
about going down קדושה k'dusha were not a problem, עושין, osin, you
could use the ספר תורה Sefer Torah for your מזוזה. mezuza.
אמאי הכא סתומות הכא פתוחות? amai hacha stumot hacha p'tuchot? In the
ספר תורה Sefer Torah it appears סתום satum and here it appears
פתוח. patuach. So it must be that you're allowed to do סתום,
satum, even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would admit you're allowed to do
סתום. satum. Now of course the bizarre thing is, but they're not
juxtaposed in the תורה, Torah, so what are you doing? Are you
cutting them out and sewing them together? Are you taking the whole
text from שמע Shema all the way through והיה אם שמוע V'haya
Im Shamoa and wrapping it up and putting it in your מזוזה?
mezuza? But the גמרא Gemara is assuming maybe? I don't know, I
mean some they used to. Whether we can or not. I don't
know what the גמרא Gemara is assuming, but somehow it's assuming though
that
you are... maybe it assumes you're cutting them out and sewing it
together, but if you're cutting and sewing, you're maintaining the סתום. satum.
It's a funny question because it doesn't appear that way in the
תורה Torah text. But the גמרא Gemara is saying, ah, but fundamentally
you can transfer if not the problem of מורידין, moridin, and you
see you use it the way it appears in the תורה, Torah,
you see you can do סתום. satum. Even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
must agree to this. So the גמרא Gemara says:
ואמאי הכא סתומות והכא פתוחות? ve'amai hacha stumot vehacha p'tuchot? So the
גמרא Gemara says: לא, דילמא להשלים. lo, dilma l'hashlim. Maybe we only
mean when you're coming to supplement. Now what does supplement mean? So
this רש"י Rashi says means exactly this: your מזוזה mezuza has the
והיה אם שמוע, V'haya Im Shamoa, you want to add the שמע
Shema from the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, or the reverse: it has
the שמע, Shema, you want to add the והיה אם שמוע. V'haya
Im Shamoa. So since you're only adding it, maybe you're not making
it a סתום. satum. Maybe you're adding it at the top or
adding it at the bottom and actually doing a whole line break
between them and doing a פתוח. patuach. Okay, then what was it
thinking before? Even if you're getting both פרשיות parshiyot from the תורה,
Torah, you had to do some cutting and pasting. So that's why
I think it sounds like the הוה אמינא hava amina was you
were taking the entire section from the middle of ואתחנן, Va'etchanan, you
know, all the way through the middle of עקב, Ekev, right, and
rolling that whole thing up. But what you can prove from that,
I don't know. Anyway, this is now going to turn the גמרא
Gemara into this discussion of מורידין, moridin, but in the end we
rule that you make the... as our מזוזות mezuzot are, you make
it סתום, satum, but בדיעבד b'diavad פתוח patuach is okay. Just to
give you a little sense of the range of possibilities of what
פתוח patuach and סתום satum are, take a quick look here at
the תוספות Tosafot והיינו מנהג עלמא. vehainu minhag alma. We're a little
behind, but I just want to read you one line from this
תוספות Tosafot at the top of the page here. והיינו מנהג עלמא,
Vehainu minhag alma, he says the following. פירש בקונטרס שיש כתוב בתחילת
שיטה ובסוף שיטה Peirash b'kuntres sheyesh katuv bit'chilat shita u'v'sof shita and
let me just see... that is of course רש"י. Rashi.
He says like this: ואנו נוהגים, Ve'anu nohalogim,
like the end of the first narrow line in תוספות, Tosafot, ואנו
נוהגים להניח חלק מעט בתחילת שיטה ואחר כך מתחיל והיה אם שמוע
ושמא גם זה קרוי סתומה. Ve'anu nohalogim lehaniach chalak me'at bit'chilat shita
v'achar kach matchil V'haya Im Shamoa v'shema gam ze karui stuma.
So he has סתום satum actually means what we would call indenting,
which is interesting. You actually do start the next פרשה parsha a
little bit in, you know, and that way it would seem like
a bigger break if you've indented, but he says that maybe that
is סתום satum as well as opposed to a whole line feed
and then starting at the beginning of the next line. ורבינו תם
מפרש שקורין שמה שמסיים מסיים פרשה באמצע שיטה ומניח עד סוף השיטה
כשיעור למשפחותיהם זו היא פתוחה. V'Rabbeinu Tam mefarash shekorin shema shemesayeim mesayeim
parsha b'emtza shita u'maniach ad sof hashita k'shiur l'mishpachoteihem zu hi p'tucha.
ואם לא הניח בסוף שיטה כשיעור חרת ve'im lo hiniach b'sof shita
k'shiur cheret so maybe it has to do with the size of
the break and he goes into many many different variants, but the
two in my mind that stuck out in particular were one what
you would call indenting, starting not at the beginning of a line
but a few
letters in, a few spaces in, and the other was an entire
line feed. You would go to the end, you'd end the פסוק
pasuk in the middle, go to the end of the line and
have an entire blank line after. And that actually apparently they did
find in some of the Dead Sea Scrolls.
So ואנו נוהגים ve'anu nohalogim what he's saying is that if you
have a סתום, satum,
you just basically you keep פתוח patuach to the rest of the
end and then indent?
That's what he's saying, is that then you sort of have the
text bracketing the whitespace. So it also is, and then I was
saying... was not universally standardized. Okay, so again it shows you how
much some of these things are referred to in the גמרא Gemara
but I don't know the whole history about how those things solidified.
Okay, let's get back to the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara
says המרידין אותן hamaridin otan now we're going to get to the
question about what type of קלף klaf you write it on. So
now back to this point, in theory, if there were not a
problem of higher and lower קדושה, kedusha, you could use ספר תורה
Sefer Torah and תפילין Tefillin for your מזוזה. mezuzah. One minute, we've
got a problem, they're written in different ways. והתניא ve-hatanya we're taught
in the ברייתא, beraita, הלכה למשה מסיני halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai and here's
the first time we are connecting it to הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha
le-Moshe mi-Sinai.
תפילין על הקלף ומזוזה על דוכסוסטוס. Tefillin al ha-klaf u-mezuzah al duchsostos.
תפילין Tefillin is written on the קלף klaf and מזוזה mezuzah on
the דוכסוסטוס. duchsostos. What's the קלף klaf and what's the דוכסוסטוס? duchsostos?
So it's going to say in a minute, קלף במקום בשר, דוכסוסטוס
במקום שיער. klaf be-makom basar, duchsostos be-makom se'ar. The קלף klaf is
where the skin of the animal is and the דוכסוסטוס duchsostos where
the hair is. So what does this mean? It means the following,
that basically you would have let me just double check this because
I get this confused one minute.
Basically, what you would have is you would have the thickness of
the leather that you took from the animal. This would be the
thickness of the leather. Now the way the גמרא Gemara describes it
is that basically you would split this leather in two. Okay? So
after you've split it in two, do you use the part that
was this is the animal itself. Do you use the part that
was closer to the inner of the animal or do you use
the part that was closer to the outside of the animal? That's
one question.
To the
meat?
You said to the skin. Oh, sorry, to meat of the animal.
The other question is which part of this leather do you use?
This part or this part? קלף, klaf, the question is which side
do you use? So קלף klaf is the part of the skin
that's closest to the animal and the גמרא Gemara says you use
the מקום בשר, makom basar, you use where it touched the actual
flesh of the animal itself. דוכסוסטוס duchsostos is the part of the
leather that was at the outer part of the animal, this, and
you use the מקום שיער. makom se'ar. So basically you use the
two extremes, part either facing the hair or facing the meat and
you split it in half. Those are the two types of קלף
klaf you can use. So let's take a look.
Isn't that what we're clear? Is parchment or were we talking about
cutting out a piece of a ספר תורה? Sefer Torah?
Cutting out a piece of a ספר תורה Sefer Torah and putting
it in your תפילין. Tefillin. Or cutting up the שמע Shema and
putting it in your תפילין. Tefillin.
So it's like recycling.
Right, exactly. And the הלכה halacha is you're not allowed to recycle
because you can't go down a קדושה. kedusha. You could upcycle, whatever
it is, upgrade. If you have מזוזה, mezuzah, you needed it for
תפילין Tefillin or something, you could take out the שמע Shema from
your מזוזה mezuzah and put it into תפילין Tefillin if you paid
attention to the כסדראן ke-sidran concerns and so on.
This relates to what we discussed briefly yesterday about first of all
you pointed out yesterday there's more precision required in writing a מזוזה
mezuzah than writing a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah.
In terms of כסדראן, ke-sidran, right, yeah, right, you have to be
much more careful, that's right. Right.
So you would think that in process there's a higher level of
something for a מזוזה mezuzah than a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. Right.
And the second is it goes to the essence of what these
objects are,
which you said you might address someday.
Well
I have to think
about that furthermore,
but in terms of the מזוזה, mezuzah, it is funny, the ספר
תורה Sefer Torah has greater קדושה, kedusha, there are some more requirements
by מזוזה mezuzah like כסדראן, ke-sidran, and we're actually going to see
in a minute there's a whole discussion that תוספות Tosafot says that
there might not be a requirement of שרטוט shirtut by ספר תורה,
Sefer Torah, the scoring, the inside, the like,
that they use but not the lines that they make now with
ink, the lines that they make to guide them. So there are
places in which we do find some more requirements by מזוזה. mezuzah.
There's a famous line in the גמרא Gemara by מגילה Megillah that
it says the מגילה Megillah needs to have שרטוט shirtut because it
says דברי שלום ואמת divrei shalom ve-emet כאמיתה של תורה. ke-amitah shel
Torah. So what does אמיתה של תורה amitah shel Torah mean? So
רש"י Rashi says it means a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. But תוספות
Tosafot says no, a ספר תורה Sefer Torah doesn't require שרטוט shirtut
and אמיתה של תורה amitah shel Torah means the מזוזה. mezuzah. So
it's actually interesting that a מזוזה mezuzah is being called אמיתה של
תורה, amitah shel Torah, which means almost like it's the distillation of
the תורה, Torah, right? Listen to God, accept the God through the
מצוות, mitzvot, that about summarizes the תורה. Torah. That's אמיתה של תורה.
amitah shel Torah. So to what degree, although we say it has
lesser קדושה, kedusha, which is what we're saying here, is there also
at the same time some acknowledgment of greater requirements? And I think
that is what is being addressed, touched on. So now we're saying
can you use the ספר תורה Sefer Torah for the מזוזה? mezuzah?
One minute. Even if there weren't a problem about מעלין בקודש ולא
מורידין, ma'alin ba-kodesh ve-lo moridin, we're using different parts.
We're saying you actually דווקא davka have to do that.
Yes, that's what we're saying. והתניא ve-hatanya yes, הלכה למשה מסיני halacha
le-Moshe mi-Sinai תפילין על הקלף ומזוזה על דוכסוסטוס. Tefillin al ha-klaf u-mezuzah
al duchsostos. So the תפילין Tefillin would be on the קלף klaf
which would be the part of the leather that was closer to
the to the flesh of the animal and the מזוזה mezuzah on
the דוכסוסטוס. duchsostos. קלף במקום בשר klaf be-makom basar and you would
on the קלף klaf itself you would write it from the face
part of it that faced the flesh and דוכסוסטוס במקום שיער duchsostos
be-makom se'ar on the דוכסוסטוס duchsostos where it where it were closer
to the hair. So you see you can't use from one to
the other. So the גמרא Gemara says למצוה. limitzo. No, no, no,
that's just לכתחילה. lechatchila. בדיעבד bedieved you can use the different types
of parchment. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, והתניא vehatanya we
taught in the ברייתא, braisa, שינה shina פסול, pasul, if you used
the parchment in the wrong way, you know, for the different category,
it's invalid. So the גמרא Gemara says דתפילין. detfillin. No, that only
means that you can't use
the you can't use for for מזוזה mezuzah you can use what
was written on ספר תורה sefer torah קלף, klaf, okay, which is
what sort of we're discussing, or what was written on תפילין tefillin
קלף. klaf. But you can't use the מזוזה mezuzah קלף klaf for
the תפילין, tefillin, meaning the תפילין tefillin stuff you can use for
מזוזה, mezuzah, which is essentially like a logical אף מורידין af moridin
if you would, the higher stuff, the stuff that's assigned to these
higher קדושה kedusha categories you could use for the lower, but the
stuff that was used for the lower, that you could not use
for the תפילין. tefillin. So we can't change what you use for
the תפילין, tefillin, you can change what you use for the מזוזה.
mezuzah. So here we're actually saying the מזוזה mezuzah is a little
more flexible. I'm sorry, what?
The backward way we kept attached, you could or pull yourself in
the text, you could move from the מזוזה. mezuzah.
Right, but you so here it's saying we have a problem that
says in theory you could use the תפילין tefillin parchment for the
מזוזה mezuzah except for a מורידין moridin problem. So the גמרא Gemara
says well let's learn out from that that the other aspects are
the same, the way it's written. So don't we know that you're
not allowed to use the קלפין, klafin, meaning the physical parchment is
different? So it says no, no, no, by מזוזה mezuzah you have
more latitude about you can use the different ranges of parchments. When
we say you can't change, it means the parchment used for the
תפילין tefillin have to be the very this very precise type of
parchment. But the parchment used for the מזוזה mezuzah can be a
greater range. Okay, so in theory you should be able to use
the תפילין tefillin parchment for the מזוזה mezuzah but there's a מורידין
moridin problem.
Yes? So we were saying you could use for מזוזה mezuzah תפילין?
tefillin?
That's what I was putting out
there, and now we're
saying- but I was putting out there as theoretical in terms of
מעלין, maalin, but the גמרא Gemara never said it. And now according
to the גמרא Gemara you can't because of the קלף klaf that's
wrong. Okay, fine, correct. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
והתניא vehatanya שינה בין בזה ובין בזה shina bein bezeh uvein bezeh
פסול, pasul, but one ברייתא braisa says if you changed in either
direction it's invalid, which presumably means you can't use תפילין tefillin קלף
klaf for מזוזה mezuzah or מזוזה mezuzah קלף klaf for תפילין, tefillin,
that the actual parchment is very specific for each category. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, אידי ואידי idi ve'idi בתפילין. bitfillin. When it
says you can't change either way it doesn't mean you can't use
תפילין tefillin קלף klaf for מזוזה. mezuzah. It means when you're dealing
with תפילין tefillin קלף, klaf, we don't allow for either form of
variation. What would be two forms of variation for תפילין tefillin קלף?
klaf? Let's take a look. הא דכתבינהו אקלף במקום שיער, ha dechtavinehu
aklaf bimkom sear, one would be for the תפילין tefillin that you
actually use the
קלף, klaf, which is what you're supposed to use for תפילין, tefillin,
you use the קלף, klaf, the lower part of the leather, but
you use the part that was facing out, not facing in. So
that would be invalid.
והא דכתבינהו אדוכסוסטוס במקום בשר, veha dechtavinehu aduchsustus bimkom basar, or you
use the דוכסוסטוס, duchsustus, which would be the outer part of the
leather, but you use not the part that was exposed to the
outside, the part that was pointing inside. So when it says if
you switch either way it's invalid, we don't mean that- that's not
referring to the מזוזה. mezuzah. It means when the תפילין tefillin is
very specific, it's only a very specific type of parchment, any variation
is not good. But by the מזוזה, mezuzah, in theory you can
use the type of parchment that is used for the תפילין. tefillin.
Okay, so were it not for the problem that you can't lower
קדושה, kedusha, you have greater latitude. So
here...